{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>Aristocrats in this country often had hexagonal portraits of themselves painted on their</em> <em>coffins.</em> This country's nobility was believed to descend from the Sarmatian tribe, giving rise to the culture of Sarmatism. In this country, the <em>Nihil novi</em> edict and the Henrician articles strengthened the power of its nobles. This country's legislature was often crippled by a legal right called the liberum veto. Under the Golden Liberty system, this country was effectively run by the <em>sejm</em> (pr. same) parliament. For the point, nobles called <em>szlachta</em> (<b>pr. SHLOK-tuh</b>)enjoyed extensive privilege during what country's Commonwealth with Lithuania?", "answer": "<b><u>Poland</u></b> [or  <b><u>Polish</u></b>-Lithuanian  Commonwealth;  or  <b><u>Polska</u></b>;  prompt  on  <b><u>Commonwealth</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This man was lampooned as the \"fainting general\" for supposedly passing out at the Battle of</em> <em>Contreras.</em> This president's vice president, who was inaugurated in Cuba and died of tuberculosis while in office, was William Rufus King. In reference to his home state, supporters of this politician established \"Granite Clubs.\" This president defeated Winfield Scott and was supported by a slogan mentioning that \"we polked you in '44.\" For the point, name this victor in the election of 1852 who was succeeded by James Buchanan.", "answer": "Franklin <b><u>Pierce</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This movie was written by the Epstein twins, who temporarily left early on to work on Frank</em> <em>Capra's Why We Fight series</em>. A minor character in this film is the petty criminal Ugarte, who obtained two letters obtained from dead couriers. After the antagonist is killed, a police officer in this film announces \"round up the usual suspects\" and is later told \"I think this is the beginning of a beautiful friendship.\" At the end of this movie, the protagonist helps freedom fighter Victor Laszlo and his wife Ilsa escape the Nazis. For the point, name this 1942 film about Rick Blaine's nightclub in the title African city.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Casablanca</u></b></em>  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This man captured Aeclanum in a conflict sparked by the assassination of Marcus Livius</em> <em>Drusus.</em> This man persuaded Bocchus I of Mauretania to betray an opponent while he was serving under a future rival. He later received a Grass Crown for winning the Social War. He won the First Mithridatic War and defeated rivals at Colline Gate. This first dictator for life was also the first to introduce proscription and the first Roman to march on Rome with his army. For the point, name this Roman general who was rivals with Gaius Marius.", "answer": "Lucius Cornelius <b><u>Sulla</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>Peter Ward developed an alternative idea to this idea named for Medea</em>. A computer simulation to test this idea features two organisms: black and white daisies. The books <em>The</em> <em>Greening of Mars</em> and <em>A Rough Ride to the Future</em> were written by this idea\u2019s formulator, James Lovelock, to advance it. Evidence for this idea includes the constant salinity of the ocean and steady levels of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. For the point, name this hypothesis that suggests our planet is alive, and which takes its name from the ancient Greek embodiment of \u201cearth.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Gaia</u></b> Hypothesis  {II}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "<em>The rebellious governor Postumus created a breakaway empire named for this region that was</em> <em>eventually suppressed by Aurelian.</em> Brennus led people from this region to victory against Rome at the Allia River before sacking the city in 390 BC. Ambiorix led a rebellion during a war in this region, which contained administrative centers at Narbo Martius and Lugdunum. One historian described this region as \u201cdivided into three parts,\u201d inhabited by the Belgae, Aquitani, and Celts. For the point, name this region which was annexed by Rome after the defeat of Vercingetorix by Julius Caesar, who wrote a history about his conquest.", "answer": "<b><u>Gaul</u></b> [or <b><u>Gallia</u></b>; accept <b><u>Gallia</u></b> Narbonensis or <b><u>Gallia</u></b> Lugdunensis]  {II}", "metadata": "SL"}, {"question": "<em>The plaintiff in this case hired attorney Henry Weismann, who described locations as \"well</em> <em>ventilated\" and \"always sweet smelling.\"</em> The majority opinion in this case claimed a certain trade \"has never been regarded as an unhealthy one\" and was written by Rufus Peckham. A dissent in this case insisted that the \"Fourteenth Amendment does not enact Mr. Herbert Spencer's <em>Social Statics</em>.\"For the point, name this 1905 Supreme Court case defending \"liberty of contract,\" which struck down a New York law limiting the number of hours a baker could work each day.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Lochner</u></b> v. New York</em> [or <em>New York v.</em> <em><b><u>Lochner</u></b></em>]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Gerard of Cremona translated several writings from this language, including the</em> <em>pharmacology treatise De Gradibus.</em> A writer in this language claimed that a wad of cotton placed next to fire burns because of God, not fire, in a twenty-chapter work attacking an entire school of thought, incurring the blistering response <em>The Incoherence of the Incoherence</em>. A father of philosophy in this language studied at the House of Wisdom. Writers in this language translated Aristotle, thereby keeping Greek thought alive during the Dark Ages. For the point, name this language of al-Kindi, which flourished in medieval Cairo and Baghdad.", "answer": "<b><u>Arabic</u></b> [or al-<b><u>arabi</u></b>yyah]  {II}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em>A reverse version of this entity was implemented in Delaware by Patty Cannon's gang.</em> This system assisted John Price after he was rescued by US marshals in Oberlin, Ohio. Levi Coffin was an important agent of this system. A sailor named Peg Leg Joe was supposedly involved in this system, which is the subject of myths which claim that participants used codes made from blankets and sang \"Follow the Drinking Gourd.\" The nickname \"Moses\" was given to a leader of this system, Harriet Tubman. For the point, name this network used by escaped slaves.", "answer": "<b><u>Underground Railroad</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<b>Warning: 2 Answers Required!</b><em>These two countries fought the Torstenson War, a late</em> <em>phase of the Thirty Years' War</em>. One of these two countries built the G\u00f6ta Canal so ships could avoid tolls levied by the other. In 2000 a bridge opened which connected these two countries across the \u00d8resund. These are the two southernmost of the 3 modern-day countries originally part of the Kalmar Union. For the point, name these two countries whose cities of Malm\u00f6 and Copenhagen are linked by a bridge and tunnel.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Sweden</u></b> and Kingdom of <b><u>Denmark</u></b> [accept <b><u>Sverige</u></b> for \"Sweden\" and <b><u>Danmark</u></b> for \"Denmark\"; accept <b><u>Denmark-Norway</u></b> or <b><u>Danmark-Norge</u></b> in place of \"Denmark\" until \"G\u00f6ta Canal\" is read]  {II}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>Matthew Hopkins gained an epithet for his participation in this activity.</em> Cornelius Loos and Friedrich Spee (<b>pr. SHPAY</b>) protested against some of the largest of these events, which occurred in Trier and Wurzburg in the 16th and 17th centuries, respectively. These events grew in popularity after the spread of Henrich Kramer's book <em>Malleus Maleficarum</em>, which detailed the activities of this event's subjects. These events focused on finding people who were said to consort with the Devil in Sabbaths. For the point, in what events did people search for alleged magic users, often killing them afterwards?", "answer": "<b><u>witch trial</u></b>s [or <b><u>witch hunt</u></b>s]  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>A proclamation read during this event ended with a call for the nation to \u201cprove itself worthy</em> <em>of the august destiny to which it is called.\u201d</em> The perpetrators of this event read their proclamation at the General Post Office. It included fierce fighting at Mount Street Bridge. This event began three days after the arrest of Sir Roger Casement, and was led by Tom Clarke and Patrick Pearse. The year after this event, Eamon de Valera became president of Sinn F\u00e9in (<b>pr. shin fain</b>). For the point, name this Dublin insurrection named for a holiday in 1916.", "answer": "<b><u>Easter Rising</u></b> [or <b><u>Easter Rebellion</u></b>; accept similar answers]  {II}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>This state\u2019s Grand Dragon John Galen Locke engineered the election of Clarence Morley as</em> <em>governor of this state in 1924.</em> This present-day state was the location of an 1868 event in which approximately 150 Cheyenne Indians were massacred by troops under John Chivington, the Sand Creek Massacre. Cripple Creek was a popular mining settlement during this state\u2019s gold rush. This state later developed a successful ski industry along I-70 including resorts such as Copper and Vail. For the point, name the state in which Katherine Lee Bates was inspired to write \u201cAmerica the Beautiful\u201d while viewing the landscape from the summit of Pikes Peak.", "answer": "<b><u>Colorado</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "ED"}, {"question": "<em>One ruler of this empire failed to appease Ahmad al-Mansur with gifts of gold.</em> This predecessor of the Dendi Kingdom was brought to an end in a battle where the enemies redirected a cattle stampede with gunpowder weapons. It was defeated at that battle by Judar Pasha of the Saadi dynasty who razed the salt mines at Taghaza. The founder of this empire conquered Djenne (<b>pr. Jenna</b>) after a long siege. That founder was Sunni Ali, and this empire reached its height under Askia Muhammad II. For the point, name this West African empire centered at Gao which succeeded the Mali Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Songhai</u></b> Empire  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>Holders of this position used a boat called the bucentaur.</em> This position shared power with the secretive Council of Ten and a body called the Quarantia. On Ascension Day, holders of this position would throw a ring into the ocean in the Marriage of the Sea ceremony. At the age of ninety, a blind holder of this position engineered the sack of Zara and redirected the Fourth Crusade to Constantinople. That holder of this position was Enrico Dandolo. For the point, name this position that governed a \"Most Serene Republic,\" the city of Venice.", "answer": "<b><u>doge</u></b>s [prompt on answers like <b><u>ruler of Venice</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This modern-day state was the site of the majority of fighting in Father Rale\u2019s War.</em> The boundaries of this modern-day state were not set by the Treaty of Utrecht, leading to war with the French-backed Wabanaki Confederacy after fort construction near the Kennebec River. The unrecognized Republic of Madawaska bordered this state. The border of this state with the Canadian province of New Brunswick led to the Aroostook War and was resolved by the Webster-Ashburton Treaty. For the point, name this northeasternmost continental US state.", "answer": "<b><u>Maine</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "PL"}, {"question": "<em>This person used the cover name \u201cMorland\u201d while resisting invaders.</em> It's not Charles De Gaulle, but this person began a \u201ccrossing of the desert\u201d after losing his seat in 1958. He became President with his \u201c110 Propositions\u201d after becoming leader of his party in the Epinay Congress. This person abolished the death penalty with the Badinter Act. He ordered a bombing of a group who criticized his nuclear weapons testing in the South Pacific and allied with other coalitions in two \u201cCohabitations.\u201d For the point, name this French Socialist Prime Minister who ordered the sinking of the Greenpeace Ship \u201cRainbow Warrior.\u201d", "answer": "Francois Maurice Adrien Marie <b><u>Mitterrand</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>This publication used Lennart Nillson\u2019s photograph of a fetus in an amniotic sac for the</em> <em>cover of one issue.</em> The cover of its inaugural issue featured two men inspecting the base of the Fort Peck Dam in a photograph by Margaret Bourke-White. While on assignment in Southeast Asia for this publication, Robert Capa was killed in the First Indochina War. Earlier, Capa had taken iconic images of the D-Day landings for this publication. It was purchased by <em>Time</em>\u2019s Henry Luce in 1936, and also published a photo of a sailor kissing a nurse in Times Square on V-J Day. For the point, name this now-defunct magazine known for its photojournalism.", "answer": "<em><b><u>LIFE</u></b> Magazine</em> [accept <em><b><u>Time-Life</u></b></em>]  {II}", "metadata": "SL"}, {"question": "<em>After being deposed, one ruler of this empire fought his brother Kamran.</em> The second ruler of this empire was defeated at Kannauj by Sher Shah of Sur; his son defeated the usurper Hemu. It reached its greatest size after the Deccan kingdoms of Bijapur and Golconda were conquered by Aurangzeb. This empire was founded by a man who defeated the Delhi Sultanate at the First Battle of Panipat, Babur. Its greatest ruler was Babur\u2019s grandson, Akbar. For the point, name this Indian empire whose name reflects its Mongol origins.", "answer": "<b><u>Mughal</u></b> Empire  {II}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>This team offered a $15,000 bonus to a 1938 draft pick who was an Oxford Rhodes scholar</em>. Future Supreme Court justice Byron White played for this NFL team. In 1974, this squad drafted four Hall of Famers in one year. During a playoff game, a pass intended for John Fuqua ended up in the hands of Franco Harris, who scored on this team's \"Immaculate Reception.\" This team's Hall of Famers have included \"Mean\" Joe Greene and quarterback Terry Bradshaw. It has won more Super Bowl championships than any other team. For the point, name this AFC North football team from Pennsylvania.", "answer": "Pittsburgh <b><u>Steelers</u></b> [or <b><u>Pittsburgh</u></b> Steelers; or Pittsburgh <b><u>Pirates</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>One member of this organization was the Polish martyr Andrew Bobola.</em> This organization\u2019s founder and his six companions took vows at Montmartre. One leader of this organization, Claudio Aquaviva, published its <em>Ratio Studiorum,</em> or \u201cplan of studies.\u201d This organization\u2019s rules were set forth in its <em>Formula of the Institute.</em> Its creation was approved by Pope Paul III. The founder of this order was a Spanish soldier who was wounded in battle and wrote the <em>Spiritual</em> <em>Exercises.</em> For the point, name this Catholic order founded by St. Ignatius of Loyola.", "answer": "<b><u>Jesuit</u></b>s [or <b><u>Society of Jesus</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>In 1970, Richard Nixon went to this location at 4:15 A.M. to talk with student protesters</em>. An event at this place was arranged after both protests by Charles Hamilton Houston's MACC group and Walter White's organization. Harold Ickes and Eleanor Roosevelt arranged for an event here after an earlier site was quashed by the Daughters of the American Revolution. In 1939, after being banned from performing at Constitution Hall, black singer Marian Anderson performed on the steps of this location. For the point, name this structure on the National Mall that honors the 16th President.", "answer": "<b><u>Lincoln Memorial</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>National Mall</u></b> until mentioned]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>The capture of this kingdom\u2019s capital was assisted by an army sailing from England to the</em> <em>Second Crusade</em>. One of this kingdom\u2019s dynasties was created after John I won the Battle of Aljubarrota. The earlier Battle of Ourique (<b>pr. oo-REE-kay</b>) led to the creation of this kingdom by Afonso Henriques. This kingdom, which was ruled by the Aviz Dynasty, was granted all new lands east of a meridian line determined by Pope Alexander VI in the Treaty of Tordesillas (<b>pr. </b> <b>tor-diss-EE-uhs</b>). For the point, name this Iberian kingdom that sponsored Vasco da Gama.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Portugal</u></b> and the Algarves  {II}", "metadata": "SL"}, {"question": "<em>A man who lived in this state dated teenage widow Nicole Baker after being paroled from an</em> <em>Illinois prison</em>. This state is home to a film festival sponsored by Robert Redford which is named for a character Redford famously played. This state is where ancestry.com is headquartered and is where the land speed record was once set by the Blue Flame on the Bonneville Salt Flats. A sporting event in this state was run by a committee led by the CEO of Bain Capital. For the point, name this Western US state that hosted the 2002 Winter Olympics in Salt Lake City.", "answer": "<b><u>Utah</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Ezra Vogel wrote a controversial 2011 biography of this man titled for the transformation of</em> <em>his nation.</em> This man announced a program known as the Four Modernizations. Zhou Enlai suggested that this man be rehabilitated following his purging during the Cultural Revolution. This man proposed the \u201cone country, two systems\u201d arrangement, and he gained power by outmaneuvering Hua Guofeng in 1978. For the point, identify this leader of China who oversaw the PRC\u2019s economic liberalization in the 1980s as well as the Tiananmen Square massacre.", "answer": "<b><u>Deng</u></b> Xiaoping (accept pronunciation of either \u201cDung\u201d or \u201cDeng\u201d) [or <b><u>Teng</u></b> Hsiao-p\u2019ing]  {II}", "metadata": "ED"}, {"question": "<em>Wheeler and Feynman showed that one set of constructs named for this man admits both</em> <em>\u201cretarded\u201d and \u201cadvanced\u201d solutions to derive their absorber theory.</em> This man determined that since Saturn\u2019s rings were not solid or fluid, they were instead a collection of tiny particles. Oliver Heaviside reformulated 12 of this man\u2019s equations into their modern form, one of which contains a term for displacement current. Using Faraday\u2019s ideas of lines of force, this man published a paper which included Ampere\u2019s law, and Gauss\u2019 laws. For the point, give this namesake of a set of four equations which govern electromagnetism.", "answer": "James Clerk <b><u>Maxwell</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "<em>One side in this conflict sought to install the Terijoki Government to rule the opposing</em> <em>country.</em> This war began soon after an incident in which one side tried to frame the other for the shelling of Mainila. The losing side in this war initially won defensive efforts at Raate Road and Suomussalmi. The eventual winners in this war sought to cross the Mannerheim Line. A part of Karelia was ceded to the victors of this war in the Moscow Peace Treaty. For the point, name this war fought during the early stages of WWII between the Soviet Union and Finland.", "answer": "<b><u>Winter War</u> </b> {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>This man made a controversial 1962 appearance on Howard K. Smith's television show to</em> <em>discuss a man who had lost the governorship of California</em>. This person was harmed by experts insisting his typewriter matched the \"Baltimore documents.\" He was the executive secretary of the Dumbarton Oaks Conference. This man's assertions not to know \"George Crosley\" were disproven by the \"Pumpkin Papers.\" This man was convicted of perjury in connection with charges brought by Whittaker Chambers, who testified before HUAC. For the point, name this State Department official accused of being a Soviet spy in 1948.", "answer": "Alger <b><u>Hiss</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This government issued the Decree on Hostages in retaliation for the execution of prisoners</em> <em>of war.</em> This government lost control of Fort Issy shortly before its enemy\u2019s main attack, during which suspected traitor Jaroslav Dombrowski was killed. Gustave Courbet was blamed after supporters of this government tore down the Vend\u00f4me Column. The Bloody Week ended this government after Patrice MacMahon used Baron Haussmann\u2019s renovated streets to execute the orders of Adolphe Thiers. For the point, name this socialist government that ruled the capital of France following the Franco-Prussian War.", "answer": "<b><u>Paris Commune</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "SL"}, {"question": "<em>Employees of this company documented their World War II experiences in the books Berlin</em> <em>Diary and London After Dark.</em> An employee of this company had the wartime catchphrase \"This is London.\" Lyndon Johnson apocryphally said he had lost \"Middle America\" after seeing an employee of this company declare that the Vietnam War needed to end in 1968. Another of its employees used the show <em>See It Now</em> to attack Joseph McCarthy. For the point, name this broadcasting company whose news division has employed Edward R. Murrow and Walter Cronkite.", "answer": "<b><u>CBS</u></b> [or the <b><u>Columbia Broadcasting System</u></b>; prompt on the <b><u>Eye</u></b> Network; prompt on the <b><u>Tiffany</u></b> Network]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This theologian's sermons are collected in his</em> Postilla adumbrata<em>, while his beliefs were</em> <em>written down in his</em> De Ecclesia<em>.</em> This man became the leader of the Bethlehem Chapel, but was forced to leave that position after protesting against antipope John XXIII's sale of indulgences. The Moravian Church originated out of this man's followers. This man's teachings were heavily influenced by those of John Wycliffe, although because of this he was convicted of heresy and burned at the stake at the Council of Constance. For the point, name this Bohemian theologian.", "answer": "Jan <b><u>Hus</u></b> [or John <b><u>Hus</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>This industry was affected by a winter known as the Great Die-Up.</em> Samuel Maverick was known for his curious practices in this industry. An invention of Joseph Glidden severely affected this industry, for which the \"chuck wagon\" was invented by Charles Goodnight. The song \"Get Along Little Doggies\" derives from this industry, the products of which were transported to railways in Kansas along routes like the Chisholm trail. For the point, name this industry in which a certain livestock was herded on the open range.", "answer": "<b><u>cattle</u></b> industry [or <b><u>beef</u></b> industry; or <b><u>ranch</u></b>ing; or anything mentioning <b><u>cow</u></b>s; prompt on \"meat industry\"; do not accept or prompt on \"meatpacking\"]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>Juan de Betanzos was married to a former wife of this ruler, who took revenge on an enemy</em> <em>by torturing Atoc.</em> This ruler was killed despite the forces of his general Ruminahui nearby. In order to avoid being burned at the stake, he converted to Christianity with the help of Vincente de Valverde. With the help of his general Quizquiz, he was victorious at the battle of Quipaipan, winning a civil war against his brother, Huascar. This ruler offered to fill a ransom room with precious materials after being captured at Cajamarca. For the point, name this ruler of the Incan empire who was captured by Francisco Pizarro.", "answer": "<b><u>Atahualpa</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>In 2014, this agency issued a report that claimed the construction of the Keystone pipeline</em> <em>would not significantly affect climate change.</em> This agency established the first QDDR in 2010. The term \"smart power\" was popularized by a head of this agency during her confirmation testimony. In 2009, this agency announced its policy plan of a \"pivot to Asia.\" A leader of this department claimed that the use of tear gas in Syria \"defies any code of morality\" and crossed a \"red line.\" This department is headquartered in the Harry S Truman Building. For the point, name this U.S. Cabinet department led recently by Hillary Clinton and John Kerry.", "answer": "United States Department of <b><u>State</u></b> [or the <b><u>State</u></b> Department]  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>An early chapter in this novel lists Chateaubriand and the \"Infamous Gregoire\" among every</em> <em>celebrity and fad of the year 1817.</em> In this novel, the death of real general Jean-Augustine Lamarque is mourned by the Society of the ABC. At the end of its chapter on Waterloo, a man named Pomtmercy has his life saved by the thief Thenardier (<b>pr. tair-nar-DYAY</b>). An actual rebellion in June 1832, is fictionalized in this novel as a group of students joined by Marius who build a barricade before they are all shot. For the point, name this sprawling historical novel focused on the escaped convict Jean Valjean (<b>pr. Zhahn val-ZHAHN</b>), by Victor Hugo.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Les Miserables</u></b></em> [or <em>The</em> <em><b><u>Miserable</u></b> Ones;</em> or <em>The</em> <em><b><u>Wretched</u></b>Poor</em>; or <em>The</em> <em><b><u>Victims</u></b></em>]  {II}  <b>Extra Tossup \u2013 ONLY READ IF A QUESTION IS BOTCHED!</b> <em>George Washington Plunkitt called attempts to eliminate this practice \"the root of all evil in our</em> <em>government.\"</em> This practice was combated by a group led by Dorman Bridgman Eaton created after a law proposed by the Peace Democrat running mate of George McClellan. It was given a nickname by Senator William Marcy after the victory of the Jackson Democrats in 1828. This practice was ended on the federal level shortly after the assassination of James Garfield with the Pendleton Act, which created the Civil Service Commission. For the point, name this political practice also known as the spoils system.  ANSWER: <b><u>patronage</u></b> [accept <b><u>spoils system</u></b> until mentioned]  {II}", "metadata": "MJ"}], "bonuses": []}